<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % myent SYSTEM "subsurface-divelog.ent">
%myent;
]>
<appendix xml:id="appendix-contribution-guidelines" xreflabel="Contribution Guidelines"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Contribution Guidelines</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Where to Start</title>
        <para>We assume that you already sucessfully downloaded, installed &product; and have been
            using it to log your dives. Now you are looking for a way to contribute to the project.
            There are many opportunities for community contributions, including:</para>
        <simplelist>
            <member>Submiting <xref xlink:href="#the-user-survey"/>.</member>
            <member>Answering questions on <xref xlink:href="#the-user-forum"/>.</member>
            <member>Reporting <xref xlink:href="#bugs-and-issues"/>.</member>
            <member>Testing by running the <xref xlink:href="#lastest-builds"/> to ensure stuff
                works as it should.</member>
            <member>Developing features and enhancements.</member>
            <member>Localising the User Interface.</member>
            <member>Improving the documentation.</member>
            <member>Translating the documentation.</member>
        </simplelist>
        <para>How you decide to contribute will depend largely on what skills and expertise you
            have. The list above gives you an ordered approach to getting started.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>For the Impatient</title>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Software License</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><link xlink:href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.en.html"
                            >https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.en.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Documentation License</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><link xlink:href="https://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.0/gfdl.html"
                            >https://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.0/gfdl.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Github Repository</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><link xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface"
                            >https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Bug Tracker</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><link xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/issues"
                            >https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/issues</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Mailing List</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para><link
                            xlink:href="http://lists.subsurface-divelog.org/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/subsurface"
                            >http://lists.subsurface-divelog.org/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/subsurface</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>IRC</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>freenode #subsurface</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="the-user-survey" xreflabel="The User Survey">
        <title>The User Survey</title>
        <para>In order to develop &product; to serve its users in the best possible way, it’s
            important to have user information. After using the software for a week or so, a one-box
            user survey pops up. It is entirely optional and the user controls what, if any, data
            are sent to the project. All data the user sends is useful, and will only be used to
            steer future development and to customize the software to fit the needs of the &product;
            users. If you complete the survey, or click the option not to be asked again, that
            should be the last communication of this type you receive. However, if your diving
            and/or subsurface habits change and you wish to fill in another survey, just launch
            &product; with the <command>--survey</command> option on the command line.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="bugs-and-issues" xreflabel="Bugs and Issues">
        <title>Bugs and Issues</title>
        <para>Just as there are many things right with &product;, there are also many things wrong
            with &product;. If bugs and issues are not reported we will not necesarily get to know
            about them. We encourage the community to report bugs and issues.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Before Reporting Bugs or Issues</title>
            <para>That said, not all problems are necesarily a bug or an issue and some problems are
                &quot;known&quot; bugs and issues. We therefore ask that before reporting a
                bug/issue that you do the following:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Search <xref xlink:href="#the-user-forum"/> to see whether anyone else has
                        encountered the same problem. There may be a solution already discussed and
                        solved that may save you from frustration or moving forward with using
                        &product;.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Search the <link
                            xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/issues">Bug
                            and Issue Tracker</link> for an existing report on the
                        subject/topic.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>When searching <xref xlink:href="#the-user-forum"/> and <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/issues">Bug and
                    Issue Tracker</link> comes up empty handed, then we ask that you:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Post a question on <xref xlink:href="#the-user-forum"/> and discuss with
                        the community. It may well be that something was missed and you have helped
                        uncover a bug or an issue, in which case</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>you will generally be ask to report your discovery to the <link
                            xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/issues">Bug
                            and Issue Tracker</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <note>
                <para>While a bug or issue may irritate you. Not all bugs and issues are equal. Some
                    bugs are more equal than others and will therefore take precedence over those
                    that are less equal.</para>
                <para>Community contributions are done on a volunteer basis. The pace at which fixes
                    or enhancements happen is therefore subject to &quot;doing it yourself&quot; or
                    waiting for somebody else wanting to &quot;scratch an itch&quot;.</para>
            </note>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Reporting Bugs and Issues</title>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Be precise</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Keep it short and on topic.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Try reproduce</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Try to reproduce your bug using a recent version of the software, to
                            see whether it has already been fixed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Give context</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Specify what operating system you are using and what version of
                            &product; you are using. Specify what dive computer you are using or
                            what is the source of your divelogs.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Be clear</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Explain how to reproduce the problem, step by step, so others can
                            reproduce the bug, or understand the request.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Be specific</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Include only one problem per task.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Testing</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Latest Release</title>
            <para>If you want the sources for the latest release, the archives and precompiled
                binaries are available from <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/releases/latest"
                    >Latest Release Tag</link> on Github.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Test Versions</title>
            <para>Test versions of &product; are available from the <link
                    xlink:href="http://subsurface-divelog.org/downloads/test/">Dev/Test
                    Builds</link> page.</para>
            <para>These are builds of the HEAD of origin/master (plus some other random files),
                uploaded roughly &quot;whenever Dirk remembers to do so&quot;.</para>
            <warning>
                <para>Test Versions are intended primarily for the &product; testers - use at your
                    own risk.</para>
            </warning>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="lastest-builds" xreflabel="Latest Builds">
            <title>Latest Builds</title>
            <para>If you want the latest pre-release release build, the archives and precompiled
                binaries are available from <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/releases/tag/continuous"
                    >Continuous Tag</link> on Github.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Developing</title>
        <para>If you would like to contribute patches that fix bugs or add new features, that is of
            course especially welcome. If you are looking for places to start, look at the open bugs
            in our <link xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/issues">Bug
                and Issue Tracker</link>.</para>
        <note>
            <para>You will need to know something about working with Git and Github. The sections
                below are just to give you some hints on how to proceed and what is expected when
                submitting source contributions.</para>
        </note>
        <sect2>
            <title>Getting the Source</title>
            <para>You can get the latest development version (origin/master) from the project git
                repository.</para>
            <screen>
$ git clone https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface.git
            </screen>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Creating a Working Branch</title>
            <para>You will need to create a working branch in which you can keep your development.
                You can name your working branch anything you like. We recommend keeping the name
                short, simple and related; that way the name will mean more and give a hint as to
                what the intent of the work is about.</para>
            <para>At the command line use the commands below to create a working branch. The example
                commands below use <command>my-branch-name</command> as the name of the working
                branch. Replace <command>&lt;my-branch-name&gt;</command> with a name of your
                own.</para>
            <screen>
$ cd subsurface
$ git checkout master
$ git pull
$ git checkout -d my-branch-name
Switched to a new branch 'my-branch-name'
            </screen>
            <para>Now we can check that our branch has been created and we have switch to our new
                working branch.</para>
            <screen>
$ git branch
* my-branch-name
  master
            </screen>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Creating a Commit</title>
            <para>Once you have edited the source and you are happy that it compiles and that you
                have satisfactory tested, you can create a commit. Feel free to break your changes
                into multiple smaller commits.</para>
            <para>The following command starts a commit using your systems default editor. Usually
                you can define which by setting the environment variable <envar>GIT_EDITOR</envar>.
                The <parameter>-s</parameter> option will help you add Signed-off-by line by the
                committer at the end of the commit log message. The <parameter>-a</parameter> option
                tells the command to automatically stage files that have been modified and deleted,
                but new files you have not told Git about are not affected.</para>
            <screen>
$ git commit -s -a
            </screen>
            <para>When creating the commit there are some expectations. The commit must have:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>header line</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The first line of the commit is the subject or title. Keep it brief
                            and to the point.</para>
                        <para>That header line really should be meaningful, and really should be
                            just one line. The header line is what is shown by tools like gitk and
                            shortlog, and should summarize the change in one readable line of text,
                            independently of the longer explanation.</para>
                        <para>The preferred way to write a commit message is using <link
                                xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperative_mood"
                                >imperative mood</link>.</para>
                        <example>
                            <title>Example of Imperitive Mood</title>
                            <para>&quot;Make foo do xyz&quot; instead of &quot;This patch makes foo
                                do xyz&quot; or &quot;I made foo do xyz&quot;, as if you are giving
                                commands or requests to the code base.</para>
                        </example>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>body description</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A few lines of text, explaining things in more detail, possibly giving
                            some background about the issue being fixed, etc etc. The body of the
                            commit message can be several paragraphs, and please do proper word-wrap
                            and keep columns shorter than about 74 characters or so. That way
                            &quot;git log&quot; will show things nicely even when it is
                            indented.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Reported-by</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If working on an existing issue report, provide the name of the person
                            who reported.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Signed-off-by</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Your Name followed by Your Email Address.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <important>
                <para>If your commit is not signed, it will not be accepted. For more information
                    about the sign-off and what it means, please see <link
                        xlink:href="http://developercertificate.org/"
                        >developercertificate.org</link>.</para>
            </important>
            <para>Following is a minimal example of how a commit may look.</para>
            <screen>
Create user manual file

Created the main user manual file in docbook5 xml.

Reported-by: some-reporter
Signed-off-by: someuser &lt;someuser@example.com&gt;

On branch my-branch-name
  Changes to be committed:
    new file:   Documentation/en/subsurface-divelog.xml
            </screen>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Important Behaviour Changes</title>
            <para>When important changes are made to behaviors, fixes or new features are introduced
                an entry must be added to <filename>CHANGELOG.md</filename> file. Always add new
                entries at the very top of the file above other existing entries. Use this layout
                for new entries:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Area</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Details about the change [reference thread / issue].</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Area1/Area2</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>When multiple areas are affected list the areas separated with a
                            /</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <para>Here is a (non exhaustive) list of Areas that can be used:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Bluetooth</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Cloud-storage</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Desktop</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Dive pictures</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Import</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Libdivecomputer</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Map-widget</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Mobile</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Planner</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Printing</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Profile</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Submitting your Contribution</title>
            <para>At this point there are two ways you can go:</para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Pull Request</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This entails pushing your branch to GitHub and creating a pull
                            requests on GitHub.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Patch File</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This entails creating <filename>commit.patch</filename> files and
                            sending them to the <xref xlink:href="#mailing-list"/>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <sect3>
                <title>Creating a Pull Request</title>
                <para>To use this method you must first push your changes to Github and then <link
                        xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface/pulls">create a
                        Pull Request at the Project GitHub</link>.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Creating Patch Files</title>
                <para>Patch files are text files that consists of a list of differences. In this
                    case the difference between the origin/master branch and your working
                    branch.</para>
                <para>At the command line use the command below to create patch files. The example
                    below used <command>my-branch-name</command> as the name of the working branch.
                    Replace <command>&lt;my-branch-name&gt;</command> with a name of your
                    own.</para>
                <screen>
git format-patch master..&quot;my-branch-name&quot;
                </screen>
                <para>After running this command you will have a number of files with names like
                        <filename>0001-Commit-title.patch</filename>. These files can be archived
                    and send to the <xref xlink:href="#mailing-list"/>.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Browsing and Forking</title>
            <para>You can browse the sources and fork from the <link
                    xlink:href="https://github.com/Subsurface-divelog/subsurface">Github
                    Repository</link></para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Localising</title>
        <para>Localisations are centrally handled at <link xlink:href="https://www.transifex.com/"
                >Transifex</link>. Please sign up for an account there and then request to join the
                <link xlink:href="https://www.transifex.com/subsurface/subsurface/">Subsurface
                Team</link>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Documenting</title>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Translating</title>
    </sect1>
</appendix>
