<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % myent SYSTEM "subsurface-divelog.ent">
%myent;
]>
<chapter xml:id="chapter-overview" xreflabel="overview" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>&productshort; can plan and track single and multi-tank dives using Air, Nitrox or TriMix.
        &productshort; allows tracking of dive locations including GPS coordinates (which can also
        conveniently be entered using a map interface), logging of equipment used and names of other
        divers, and lets users rate dives and provide additional notes.</para>
    <para>You can tag dives and filter a dive list based on criteria including tags, locations and
        people with whom you were diving. You can group the dive list into trips, and edit multiple
        dives at the same time, making it easy to support a large number of dives.</para>
    <para>One of the major strengths of Subsurface is its wide range of <xref
            xlink:href="#appendix-supported-dive-computers"/>. Subsurface can also use existing dive
        logs from several <xref xlink:href="#appendix-supported-dive-software"/>.</para>
    <para>Another strength is its ability to visualize the depth profile (and, if available, the
        tank pressure curve) in innovative ways that give the user additional information on
        relative velocity, and momentary air consumption, during a dive. Users who dive with
        multiple dive computers can combine the data from each of their dive computers into one dive
        – allowing visualization of the data collected from multiple sources.</para>
    <para>&productshort; also calculates a wide variety of statistics of the user’s diving and
        tracks information like the SAC rate, partial pressures of O2, N2 and He, calculated deco
        information, and many more.</para>
    <para>Multiple divers can share one instance of Subsurface using different preferences and
        settings.</para>
    <para>The program is localized in about 20 languages and well supported by an active developer
        community.</para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Product Variants</title>
        <para>&product; software is available as desktop, mobile and web application variants. Each
            of these has been named as follows:</para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>&productdesktop;</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The full program. An executable program installed on a desktop
                        computer.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>&productmobile;</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A mobile application installed on a smart phone.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>&productcloud;</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A web application installed on the cloud and accessible by web
                        browser.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>Each variant of the software is not only designed to run on a different target
            hardware and environments, but also consistant of slight differences in
            functionality.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>&productdesktop;</title>
            <para>&productdesktop; is the name given to the full program that can be downloaded and
                installed on a computer desktop operating system such as Micoroft Windows, MacOS or
                Linux. &productdesktop; is fully featured and serves as the main program for
                recording and managing divelogs when using a desktop or laptop computer. While many
                features of &productdesktop; are also available in &productmobile;, some features
                are not. The Dive Planning module is only available in &productdesktop;.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>&productmobile;</title>
            <para>&productmobile; is the name given to the modile version of &productshort;. It can
                be downloaded and installed on a smart phone device and is partially featured. It
                serves as a more limited mobile version of &product; aimed at Android and iOS
                smartphone and tablet devices, allowing viewing, entering, sharing, and storage of
                dive information at dive sites where a larger computer is not useful.</para>
            <para>While the desktop version of &product; shows much more detailed information for
                each dive, &productmobile; allows dive logs to be more accessible on a dive trip, where it is useful
                for providing proof of dive experience to dive shops or to review dives.
                &productmobile; also allows the gathering of GPS locations where dives are performed
                using the GPS modem that is an integral part of most mobile devices.</para>
            <para>Users of &productmobile; typically use the mobile app as a companion to the
                desktop version, sharing dive information between the mobile and the desktop
                versions via the &productcloud; service. However, &productmobile; can also be used
                independently of the desktop version and does not require the use of cloud
                storage.</para>
            <para>These items are discussed in greater detail in the following text. &productmobile;
                does not support download of dive data from all the dive computers that
                &productdesktop; can. This limitation is mainly caused by the ability to access
                different type of devices on the two mobile platforms. On Android, a subset of dive
                computers that use a FTDI USB interface or a Bluetooth/Bluetooth LE interface are
                accessible by &productmobile;. On iOS, only Bluetooth LE based dive computers are
                supported.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>&productcloud;</title>
            <para>&productcloud; is the name given to the &product; web-application and cloud service. It is not
                possible to download or install &productcloud; because it is a web service that may
                be utilised by &product; and &productmobile; to backup, store and exchange divelogs
                between &product; and &productmobile;. It is accessible by a web browser. The
                web-based application interface of &productcloud; provides a read-only reporting
                interface.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Feature Comparison</title>
        <table>
            <title>Product Variants Feature Comparison</title>
            <tgroup cols="4">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Feature</entry>
                        <entry>Desktop</entry>
                        <entry>Mobile</entry>
                        <entry>Cloud</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Download divelogs direct</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Store divelogs locally</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Store divelogs on cloud</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>View divelogs</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Manually create divelogs</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Edit data fields</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Record GPS Coordinates</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Viewing recorded GPS locations on a map</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Dive Planning</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
