<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % myent SYSTEM "subsurface-divelog.ent">
%myent;
]>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title>&product;</title>
        <subtitle>User Manual</subtitle>
        <productname>&product;</productname>
        <productnumber>&productversion;</productnumber>
        <pubdate>September 2018</pubdate>
        <abstract>
            <title>About &product;</title>
            <para>&product; is an open source divelog program for recreational, technical and
                free divers that runs on Windows, Mac, Linux, Android and IOS.</para>
            <para>&product; enables the download or import of dive logs from a variety of dive
                computers, dive log programs and dive log websites. &product; also supports
                import using files formatted using comma-separated values
                (<acronym>CSV</acronym>) and the ability to manually create and save dive
                logs directly.</para>
            <para>&product; provides a visual dive planner module that makes dive planning easy
                and intuitive using a choice of Bühlmann ZH16 or Varying Permeability Model
                (<acronym>VPM-B</acronym>) decompression algorithms.</para>
            <para>&product; offers both local and cloud storage options. Using the &product;
                cloud storage option, makes it it possible for you to access your dive log data
                from different computers and mobile devices in both online and offline
                modes.</para>
        </abstract>
        <abstract>
            <title>A Bit of History</title>
            <para>In fall of 2011, when a forced lull in kernel development gave him a chance to
                start a new project, Linux creator Linus Torvalds decided to tackle his
                frustration with the lack of decent divelog software on Linux.</para>
            <para>Linus worked with a team of developers, and &product; is the result. It now
                supports Linux, Windows and MacOS and allows data import from many dive
                computers and several existing divelog programs.</para>
            <para>&product; provides a quick and easy way to see the key information provided by
                a modern dive computer and lets users track a wide variety of data about their
                dives. In fall of 2012 Dirk Hohndel took over as Subsurface maintainer.</para>
        </abstract>
        <legalnotice>
            <title>Software License</title>
            <para>&product; software is released under the <link
                xlink:href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.en.html">GNU GENERAL PUBLIC
                LICENSE</link>.</para>
        </legalnotice>
        <legalnotice>
            <title>Documentation License</title>
            <para>&product; documetation is released under <link
                xlink:href="https://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.0/gfdl.html">GNU Free
                Documentation License</link>.</para>
        </legalnotice>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>Jacco van Koll</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Dirk Hohndel</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Reinout Hoornweg</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Linus Torvalds</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Miika Turkia</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Amit Chaudhuri</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Jan Schubert</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Willem Ferguson</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Salvador Cuñat</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Pedro Neves</personname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>Sean Wheller</personname>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber/>
                <date/>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </info>
    <sect1>
        <title>Downloading &product;</title>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>Using this Manual</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Conventions used in this Manual</title>
            <para>The following typographical conventions are used in this manual:</para>
            <note>
                <para>This is a note on something.</para>
            </note>
            <important>
                <para>This is an important piece of information about something.</para>
            </important>
            <warning>
                <para>This is a warning of something to either be cautious or avoid.</para>
            </warning>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Versions of this Manual</title>
            <para>&product; renders differently on the various <xref
                xlink:href="#supported-target-devices"/>. To cater for this and make the
                documentation easier to read and reference; the documentation has been profiled
                according to the different versions of the software and thier target platforms.
                This has resulted in the following versions of this manual, each tailored to a
                specific manual:</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="getting-help" xreflabel="Getting Help">
        <title>Getting Help</title>
        <sect2 xml:id="the-user-forum" xreflabel="The User Forum">
            <title>The User Forum</title>
            <para>The <link xlink:href="http://subsurface-divelog.org/user-forum/">User
                Forum</link> is a pulically accessible Google Group where anyone can ask
                questions, post comments or make suggestions. You can access the <link
                    xlink:href="http://subsurface-divelog.org/user-forum/">User Forum</link>
                using a web browser, or you can subscribe to it via email; simply check the
                corresponding box when joining the forum. </para>
            <note>
                <para>The preferred language is English, but we will make an effort to answer
                    questions in other languages as well (not everyone is comfortable posting in
                    English … ).</para>
            </note>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 xml:id="mailing-list" xreflabel="Mailing List">
            <title>The Mailing List</title>
            <para>The <link
                xlink:href="http://lists.subsurface-divelog.org/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/subsurface"
                >Mailing List</link> is for developers and users of &product;. If you intend
                <xref xlink:href="#contributing-to-the-project"/> it is a good idea to join
                the mailing list.</para>
            <note>
                <para>Conversation there is in English -- even though this site (and &product;
                    itself) are available in many languages, the shared language we all
                    communicate in is English. Actually &quot;Broken English&quot; is just fine…
                    :-)</para>
            </note>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>IRC Freenode</title>
            <para>There are developers and users hanging out in the #subsurface channel on <link
                xlink:href="http://freenode.net/">freenode.net</link>.</para>
            <para>While there is a <application>freenode webchat</application>, use of an
                <application>IRC Client</application> application is recomended.</para>
            <para>The #subsurface channel requires that users have a registered nickname in
                order to join. Please see the <link
                    xlink:href="https://freenode.net/kb/answer/registration">freenode Nick
                    Registration</link> page for details.</para>
            <note>
                <para>While people may be always logged in to the freenode channel, they but not
                    always around - please be patient and stay around when asking questions - or
                    try <xref xlink:href="#the-user-forum"/>.</para>
            </note>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="contributing-to-the-project" xreflabel="Contributing to the Project">
        <title>Contributing to the Project</title>
        <para>As an open source project, &product; always needs and welcomes contributions from
            the wider community. There are many opportunities for community contributions, for
            more information on the opportunities for contribution we highly recomend reading
            the <xref xlink:href="#appendix-contribution-guidelines"/>.</para>
    </sect1>
</preface>

