<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % myent SYSTEM "subsurface-divelog.ent">
%myent;
]>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <preface>
        <info>
            <title>&product; User Manual</title>
            <productname>&product;</productname>
            <productnumber>&productversion;</productnumber>
            <pubdate>September 2018</pubdate>
            <abstract>
                <title>About &product;</title>
                <para>&product; is an open source divelog program for recreational, technical and
                    free divers that runs on Windows, Mac, Linux, Android and IOS.</para>
                <para>&product; enables the download or import of dive logs from a variety of dive
                    computers, dive log programs and dive log websites. &product; also supports
                    import using files formatted using comma-separated values
                        (<acronym>CSV</acronym>) and the ability to manually create and save dive
                    logs directly.</para>
                <para>&product; provides a visual dive planner module that makes dive planning easy
                    and intuitive using a choice of Bühlmann ZH16 or Varying Permeability Model
                        (<acronym>VPM-B</acronym>) decompression algorithms.</para>
                <para>&product; offers both local and cloud storage options. Using the &product;
                    cloud storage option, makes it it possible for you to access your dive log data
                    from different computers and mobile devices in both online and offline
                    modes.</para>
            </abstract>
            <abstract>
                <title>A Bit of History</title>
                <para>In fall of 2011, when a forced lull in kernel development gave him a chance to
                    start a new project, Linux creator Linus Torvalds decided to tackle his
                    frustration with the lack of decent divelog software on Linux.</para>
                <para>Linus worked with a team of developers, and &product; is the result. It now
                    supports Linux, Windows and MacOS and allows data import from many dive
                    computers and several existing divelog programs.</para>
                <para>&product; provides a quick and easy way to see the key information provided by
                    a modern dive computer and lets users track a wide variety of data about their
                    dives. In fall of 2012 Dirk Hohndel took over as Subsurface maintainer.</para>
            </abstract>
            <legalnotice>
                <title>Software License</title>
                <para>&product; software is released under the <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.en.html">GNU GENERAL PUBLIC
                        LICENSE</link>.</para>
            </legalnotice>
            <legalnotice>
                <title>Documentation License</title>
                <para>&product; documetation is released under <link
                        xlink:href="GNU Free Documentation License"
                        >https://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.0/gfdl.html</link>.</para>
            </legalnotice>
            <authorgroup>
                <author>
                    <personname>Jacco van Koll</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Dirk Hohndel</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Reinout Hoornweg</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Linus Torvalds</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Miika Turkia</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Amit Chaudhuri</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Jan Schubert</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Willem Ferguson</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Salvador Cuñat</personname>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <personname>Pedro Neves</personname>
                </author>
            </authorgroup>
            <revhistory>
                <revision>
                    <revnumber/>
                    <date/>
                </revision>
            </revhistory>
        </info>
        <sect1>
            <title>Downloading &product;</title>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
            <title>Conventions used in this Manual</title>
            <para>The following typographical conventions are used in this manual:</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
            <title>Getting Community Help</title>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
            <title>Contributing to the Project</title>
            <sect2>
                <title>Reporting Bugs</title>
            </sect2>
            <sect2>
                <title>Getting the Sources</title>
            </sect2>
        </sect1>
    </preface>
    <chapter>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>&product; can plan and track single- and multi-tank dives using air, Nitrox or TriMix.
            &product; allows tracking of dive locations including GPS coordinates (which can also
            conveniently be entered using a map interface), logging of equipment used and names of
            other divers, and lets users rate dives and provide additional notes.</para>
        <para>You can tag dives and filter a dive list based on criteria including tags, locations
            and people with whom you were diving. You can group the dive list into trips, and edit
            multiple dives at the same time, making it easy to support a large number of
            dives.</para>
        <para>One of the major strengths of Subsurface is its wide range of <xref
                xlink:href="#appendix-supported-dive-computers"/>. Subsurface can also use existing
            dive logs from several <xref xlink:href="#appendix-supported-dive-software"/>.</para>
        <para>Another strength is its ability to visualize the depth profile (and, if available, the
            tank pressure curve) in innovative ways that give the user additional information on
            relative velocity, and momentary air consumption, during a dive. Users who dive with
            multiple dive computers can combine the data from each of their dive computers into one
            dive – allowing visualization of the data collected from multiple sources.</para>
        <para>&product; also calculates a wide variety of statistics of the user’s diving and tracks
            information like the SAC rate, partial pressures of O2, N2 and He, calculated deco
            information, and many more.</para>
        <para>Multiple divers can share one instance of Subsurface using different preferences and
            settings.</para>
        <para>The program is localized in about 20 languages and well supported by an active
            developer community.</para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title/>
    </chapter>
    <xi:include href="appendix-installation.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="appendix-supported-dive-computers.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="appendix-supported-dive-software-imports.xml"/>
</book>
